让我们看一个稍微更现实的例子。
Let's have a look at a slightly more realistic example.
在这里，我有一个二维车和
Here I have a 2-dimensional car and
二维坐标系。我已经标记了这个坐标框架W代表
a 2-dimensional coordinate frame. I've labeled this coordinate frame W and that stands for
世界坐标系，这在机器人技术中是一个很常见的东西，有一个参考
the world coordinate frame and this is quite a common thing in robotics to have one reference
关于所有其他参考帧的框架。并表明
frame that all other reference frames are described with respect to. And to indicate
非常非常清楚地，我用下标W标记了x和y轴，所以就是这样
that very, very clearly, I've labeled the x and y axis with the subscript W, so it's
非常非常清楚这是W帧的x轴和W帧的y轴。
very, very clear that this is the x-axis of the W frame and the y-axis of the W frame.
现在让我们来说明这款车的一些兴趣点，左侧座椅：右侧座椅，
Now let's indicate some points of interest in this car, the left seat: the right seat,
其中一个镜子，门把手，也许还有我们加油的地方。我可以描述每个
one of the mirrors, door handles, and perhaps where we refuel it. I can describe each of
这些点由矢量，相对于世界坐标系。
these points by a vector, with respect to the world coordinate frame.
现在让我们想象一下汽车已经移动了，现在它已经结束了，我现在可以描述所有这些了
Now let's imagine that a car has moved, now it's over here, I could now describe all these
相对于世界坐标系的原点，在矢量方面再次指出。
points again in terms of vectors with respect to the origin of the world coordinate frame.
但这有点单调乏味，因为这些要点实际上并没有得到尊重
But it's a little bit tedious because the points haven't actually moved with respect
到了汽车，整辆车已经移动了，现在我必须再次重新定义所有的矢量。
to the car, the whole car has moved and now I have to redefine all the vectors again.
也许，有更好的方法。就是这样，我们将使用坐标框架
Perhaps, there's a better way. And there it is, we are going to use the coordinate frame
想法再次，我们将创建一个新的坐标框架，我将附加它
idea again and we are going to create a new coordinate frame and I'm going to attach it
去车。我把这个框架用C-C标记为汽车。为了清楚起见，我给它贴了标签
to the car. I labeled this frame C - C for car. And just to be clear, I labeled the
轴XC和YC：X和Y轴是连接到汽车的坐标系。现在是
axis XC and YC: X and Y axis are the coordinate frame that are attached to the car. Now it's
在矢量方面描述汽车上所有这些兴趣点的简单问题
a simple matter to describe all these points of interest on the car in terms of vectors
相对于汽车的坐标系。现在，如果我移动汽车，矢量已经改变了
with respect to the car's coordinate frame. Now if I moved the car, the vectors have changed
相对于世界而言，它们并没有改变汽车的坐标框架。
with respect to the world but they haven't changed with respect to the car's coordinate frame.
让我们简化一下，在这里介绍一下姿势。所以介绍另一个
Let's simplify things a bit and introduce a pose here. So introduce another one of these
表示姿势的胖箭头，这是来自世界坐标系的姿势
fat arrows which represents a pose, and this is the pose from the world coordinate frame
到了汽车的坐标框架，所以它是WksiZ.现在让我们看一下一个点
to the car's coordinate frame so it's W ksi Z. Now let's look at just a single point, one
汽车门上的点数。我要标记那个点d并且我们创建了
of the points on the door of the car. I'm going to label that point d and we created
从框架C到这一点d的向量，我们用我们已经讨论过的方式表示
vector from frame C to this point d, and we denote that in the way we've already discussed
我们使用符号P来表示我们正在谈论一个向量。C是参考框架
we use a symbol P to denote that we're talking about a vector. C is the reference frame so
这是关于帧C的向量，因此它从帧C的原点开始
this is a vector with respect to frame C, so it begins at the origin of frame C and
它到了d点。现在让我们考虑一下，我想知道这个向量是什么：
it goes to the point d. Now let's consider that I want to know what is this vector: the
点D相对于世界坐标系。什么以某种简单的方式
point D with respect to the world coordinate frame. In some sort of simplistic way, what
我想要做的是添加这两个箭头。我想继续前进，我想继续前进
I want to do is to add these 2 arrows. I want to move along here, and I want to move along
这里。但它并不那么简单，我们无法添加姿势和矢量。我们不能添加脂肪
here. But it's not quite that simple, we can't add a pose and a vector. We can't add a fat
箭头到一个细箭头。姿势和向量是不同的数学对象，所以我们需要
arrow to a thin arrow. Poses and vectors are different mathematical objects so we need
这样做要小心一点。
to do this a little bit carefully.
我们这样做的方法是引入一个新的运算符，它就是点。在这种形式主义中，我们有
The way we do it is to introduce a new operator, and it's the dot. In this formalism, we have
一个姿势，它在矢量上运行，以便将其转换为不同的坐标
a pose and it operates on a vector in order to transform it to a different coordinate
帧。这就是这个操作符点的作用：它转换了这个描述的向量
frame. That's what this operator dot does: it transforms this vector which describes
关于坐标系C的点d，描述该点的矢量
the point d with respect to the coordinate frame C, to a vector that describes the point
d相对于坐标系W.它执行坐标之间的变换
d with respect to the coordinate frame W. It performs a transformation between coordinate
帧。所有这些都是相当抽象的。我已经介绍了这个操作符点，但我没有
frames. All of this is rather abstract. I’ve introduced this operator dot, but I haven't
实际上告诉你它是什么-你会怎么编码？而且，我们介绍了这个摘要
told you actually what it is - how would you code it? And, we introduced this abstract
由希腊字母ksi描述的姿势-我还没有确切地说那是什么
pose thing described by the Greek letter ksi - and I haven't said exactly what that is
或者你如何编写或实现它。这些是以下内容
or how you could code that or implement that. These are things would get to in the following
本讲座的各节。
sections in this lecture.